A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller, Vice Presidential records, New York Office, Series 10 FA380
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller vice presidential records, New York Office, Series 10
1974-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Persico, Joseph E.
Howe, Jonathan Trumbull
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
United States. Office of the Vice President
FA380
29 Box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Biographical/Historical note
President Gerald R. Ford nominated Nelson A. Rockefeller to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon in August 1974. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 26 10
Arrangement note
This series is divided into 3 subseries:
Subseries 1: Vice Presidential Confirmation Hearings, 1974 Subseries 2: Office of the Vice President, 1975-1977 Subseries 3: Sound Recordings, 1974-1977
Scope and Contents note
When President Gerald R. Ford selected Nelson A. Rockefeller to fill the vacant vice presidency on August 20, 1974, Rockefeller's staff began preparing material for the confirmation hearings. Much of the material in this series was gathered from the Rockefeller family archives, which was located in Rockefeller Center.
Rockefeller's staff spent most of late August and early September preparing background data, developing drafts of testimony, and fulfilling requests for information from Congressional committee members. The files that begin this series are the products of those efforts.
Once he was confirmed and sworn in as Vice President, Rockefeller and his staff began to accumulate files anew. A new set of subject files was created, as well as files concerned with the daily activities of the Vice President. These files were periodically shipped to the family archives in New York for storage.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Richard Allison (FA377)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Central Files (FA378)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, National Commission on Water Quality (FA379)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Joseph E. Persico (FA381)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Press Releases (FA382)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Speeches (FA383)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Working Papers of the Vice President (FA384)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential Records, Foreign Affairs and National Security (FA385)
Social sciences; Social problems; Social policy; Public policy; Public health; Prevention and health; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1976; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; National security -- United States; International relations -- United States; United States; Veterans -- United States; International relations; Technology; Human rights; International economic relations; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; Environmental policy; Environmental sciences; Education -- United States; Energy; Economics; Education; Drug control; Economic policy; Water -- Purification; Water -- Pollution; Water conservation; Vice-Presidents -- United States; Persico, Joseph E.; Howe, Jonathan Trumbull; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); United States. Office of the Vice President
- Vice Presidential Confirmation Hearings, 1974; 1; 24 Box(es)
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged alphabetically by topic or person.
  Scope and Contents note
  These files were gathered from the Rockefeller family archives in New York to help prepare testimony and position papers on various issues for the hearings. At the end of each day of testimony, the archive staff gathered information that had been requested that day by the committees and sent it to Washington.
  - Allegations - Index (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Documents prepared in response to questions raised against NAR.
  - Allegations - Additional Information (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allegations - Bilderberg Conference (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allegations - Bilderberg Conference (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allegations - Bilderberg Conference (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Allegations - Consolidated Edison Rate Increase (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Allegations - Dictatorship and NAR (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allegations - Dunleavay, Charles A. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Allegations - Liberty Lobby (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Allegations - Perot, H. Ross (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Allegations - Rockefeller Family Power (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Allegations - State Spending Policies (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Attica - Data Compiled (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Information regarding Attica prison riot of September 1971 and NAR's handling of it.
  - Attica - "Sixty Questions About the McKay Report" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Background - Background Information (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes NAR speech excerpts on major issues; an informational packet on tax audits; an issue packet prepared by the Institute for Public Policy Awareness; and a report entitled, "The Disability of Wealth."
    General note
    Information collected to respond to possible issues that would be raised during the hearings.
  - Background - Background Materials (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes a legal brief on the legality of NAR loans to staff and employees; other loan information; list of articles, books, and other publications concerning NAR; NAR medical information supplied by Dr. Kenneth Riland; Proceedings of "Venture Capital and Management" seminar at Boston College; analysis of Library of Congress report on the record of NAR.
  - Background - Background Prepared for J. Richardson Dilworth (Box 2, Folder 17)
    A-Z index of major corporations financial status.
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Books on the history of the council published in 1937, 1947, and 1960.
  - Data on Rockefeller Organizations (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dilworth, J. Richardson (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Files that were used by Dilworth both in assisting NAR and preparing for his own testimony.
  - Dilworth, J. Richardson (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dilworth, J. Richardson (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - Dilworth, J. Richardson (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dilworth, J. Richardson (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Executive Calendar for the United States Senate (Box 3, Folder 25)
    For the date of the Senate vote
  - General Information (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Lists from Joseph W. Ernst, Rockefeller family archivist, on files in the Rockefeller family archives relating to sources of information regarding NAR and his archives that might be of use in the confirmation hearings.
  - Government Reports on the Nomination of Gerald Ford as Vice President (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Government Reports on the Nomination of Gerald Ford as Vice President (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Member Biographies (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Materials concerned with the proceedings of the U.S. House of Representatives Judiciary Committee on the nomination of NAR.
  - House Judiciary Committee - Bound volume of the hearings, November 21-22, 25-27; December 2-5, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - House Judiciary Committee - House Committee Report - Debate on the nomination, December 12, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - House Judiciary Committee - House Committee Report - Confirmation recommendation to the whole House, December 17, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - House Judiciary Committee - House Committee Print - Issues and Positions of NAR, November 1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Index to hearings (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Index to hearings (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Index to hearings (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Thursday, November 21, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Thursday, November 21, 1974, evening session (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Friday, November 22, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Friday, November 22, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Monday, November 25, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Monday, November 25, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Tuesday, November 26, 1974, afternoon session (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Tuesday, December 3, 1974, morning session (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Tuesday, December 3, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Wednesday, December 4, 1974, morning session (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Wednesday, December 4, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - House Judiciary Committee - Transcripts of Proceedings - Thursday, December 5, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Issues and Background Information - Index (Box 6, Folder 49)
    Alphabetical collection of issues that NAR was questioned about during the hearings. Includes speeches made by NAR, position papers prepared, articles, and memoranda.
  - Issues and Background Information - Listing/table of contents (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Issues and Background Information - Abortion (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Issues and Background Information - Attica (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Issues and Background Information - Attica (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Issues and Background Information - Capital Construction (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Issues and Background Information - Charitable Organizations (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Issues and Background Information - Civil Rights (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Issues and Background Information - Constitutional Powers of the Vice President (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Issues and Background Information - Critical Choices Staff (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Issues and Background Information - Drugs (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Issues and Background Information - Education (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Issues and Background Information - Estimated Net Worth of Prominent Americans (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Issues and Background Information - Executive Privilege (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Issues and Background Information - Federal Election Campaign Act Amendments, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Issues and Background Information - Ford's Pardon of Nixon (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Issues and Background Information - Gambling (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Issues and Background Information - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Memo (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Issues and Background Information - Impoundment (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Issues and Background Information - Law Enforcement (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Issues and Background Information - Mass Transit and Public Transportation (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Issues and Background Information - Mental Health (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Issues and Background Information - NAR Appointments (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Issues and Background Information - NAR Testimony before the McKay Commission (Attica) (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Issues and Background Information - No-fault Insurance (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Issues and Background Information - People on NAR Payroll (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Issues and Background Information - Press release supplementing NAR Statement of September 23, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Issues and Background Information - Prison Reform (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Issues and Background Information - Radical Left (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Issues and Background Information - Revenue Sharing (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Issues and Background Information - Rockefeller Center Inc. (Box 7, Folder 79)
    real estate taxes
  - Issues and Background Information - "The Rockefeller Record" (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Issues and Background Information - South Mall Information (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Issues and Background Information - State Campaign Laws (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Issues and Background Information - State Tax Increases (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Issues and Background Information - Status of Women (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Issues and Background Information - Text of People v. Duryea (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Issues and Background Information - Text of United States v. Nixon (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Issues and Background Information - Watergate Committee on Finance Reform (Box 8, Folder 87)
    issued report
  - Issues and Background Information - Welfare (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Issues and Background Information - Willowbrook State Hospital (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Issue Books (Box 8, Folder 90)
    Indexed volumes of various issues that were expected to be asked of NAR.
  - Issue Books (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Issue Books (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Issue Books (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Background Material (Box 8, Folder 94)
    Background material, testimony drafts, and copies of testimony for NAR's brother's testimony before the House and Senate committees.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Testimony Copy (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Testimony Copy (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Drafts (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Hearing Materials (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Testimony - Hearing Materials (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Library of Congress Reports - "Analysis of the Philosophy and Public Record of Nelson A. Rockefeller, Nominee for Vice President of the United States" (Box 9, Folder 100)
    Reports prepared by the Congressional Research Service for the hearings.
  - Library of Congress Reports - "A Brief Summary and Index of the Hearings Before the Senate Committee on Rules and Administration on the Nomination of Governor Nelson Rockefeller of the State of New York to fill the Vacancy in the Office of the Vice President of the United States on September 23, 1974" (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - NAR Comments on the Hearings (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - NAR Positions on National Defense (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - NAR Response to House Questions (Box 9, Folder 104)
  - NAR Speech File Index, 1958-1965 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    Chronological list of NAR speeches that was used to help prepare position papers on various issues.
  - NAR Speech File Index, 1966-1969 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - NAR Speech File Index, 1970-1974 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - News Summary, September 1974 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    Daily news digests summarizing the day's events, and analysis of editorials appearing in print and television.
  - News Summary, September 1974 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - News Summary, October 1974 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - News Summary, October 1974 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - News Summary, October 1974 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - News Summary, November 1974 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - News Summary, November 1974 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - "Newsweek," September 30, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 115)
    See pages 29-30; 61.
  - New York State Issues Data Submitted (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - Notes from Tapes/Index to Tapes (Box 12, Folder 117)
    Notes transcribed and index made from recordings of the hearings.
  - Personal Data - Financial (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Personal Data Submitted (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Press Comments (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - "Probing the Rockefeller Fortune" (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Public Officers Law (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Requests for and Deliveries of Information
    Material prepared by staff of the Rockefeller family office in response to requests by the House, Senate, or the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) regarding NAR.
    - Index to Personal Financial Folders of Rockefellers (Box 12, Folder 123)
      Relates to Folders 124-202
    - NAR-Venezuelan "Declaracion de Rentas", 1973 (Box 14, Folder 145)
    - Rockefeller Family Financial Records
    - Summary of Federal Tax Returns, 1964-1973 (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Summary of Tax Returns, 1964-1973 (Box 14, Folder 153)
    - Summary of Tax Returns, 1964-1973 (Box 14, Folder 154)
    - IRS Exemption Letter (Box 15, Folder 164)
    - Worksheet on Interest Income, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - Art Card (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - Summary of NAR Investments and Affiliations (Box 15, Folder 171)
    - Information re: Consolidated Edison Stock (Box 15, Folder 172)
    - NAR Recognized Gain (Box 15, Folder 175)
    - Art Expenses, 1969-1973 (Box 15, Folder 177)
    - NAR Gain on Sale of Paintings, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 179)
    - NAR Art Expenses, 1969-1973 (Box 15, Folder 180)
    - Deductibility Memo (Box 15, Folder 181)
    - Memo re: Monte Sacro (Box 15, Folder 183)
    - Memo re: Sale of Stock in NAR Farms (Box 15, Folder 184)
    - Memo re: Foreign Loans (Box 15, Folder 185)
    - Memo re: Sale of Stock in NAR Farms (Box 15, Folder 186)
    - Art Expenses, Maintenance, 1969-1973 (Box 16, Folder 190)
    - Cash Advances (Box 16, Folder 191)
    - Accounts Receivable (Box 16, Folder 193)
    - NAR - Fazenda Santa Rita Farm (Box 16, Folder 194)
    - IRS Letters on the Museum of Primitive Art (Box 16, Folder 195)
    - Third Century Corporation Data (Box 16, Folder 196)
    - Gifts, 1957-1974 (Box 16, Folder 198)
    - Open Questions from Senate Committee (Box 16, Folder 202)
    - Assets in Trusts (Box 17, Folder 216)
    - Index to Related Foundations (Box 17, Folder 225)
      Relates to Folders 226-258
    - Venrock Associates and 640 Leisure Records
    - Charitable Organizations (Box 17, Folder 235)
    - Rockefeller Foundation (RF), Annual Report, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 236)
    - Rockefeller Foundation Charter and By-Laws (Box 17, Folder 237)
    - Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF) Certificate of Incorporation (Box 17, Folder 238)
    - Rockefeller Family Fund (RFF) report, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 239)
    - Rockefeller Family Fund Certificate of Incorporation, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 240)
    - Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., Annual Report, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 241)
    - Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., Certificate of Incorporation (Box 18, Folder 242)
    - Jackson Hole Preserve, Inc., brochure (Box 18, Folder 243)
    - Museum of Primitive Art Annual Report, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 244)
    - Museum of Primitive Art Charter (Box 18, Folder 245)
    - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Box 18, Folder 246)
    - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) Charter (Box 18, Folder 247)
    - Statement on NAR's Relation to Rockefeller University (RU), Rockefeller Foundation (RF), Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF), and Rockefeller Center, Inc. (RCI) (Box 18, Folder 248)
    - "United States Business Performance Abroad" (IBEC Publication), "The AIA (American International Association) Story," by Martha Dalrymple (Box 18, Folder 249)
      Copies of cover pages only; volumes available in RAC library
    - Rockefeller Brothers Fund Annual Report, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 250)
    - Revised Statement on Rockefeller Family Fund and Rockefeller Fund (Box 18, Folder 251)
    - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Annual Reports, 1958-1973 (Box 18, Folder 252)
    - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Annual Reports, 1958-1973 (Box 18, Folder 253)
    - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) Annual Reports, 1958-1973 (Box 18, Folder 254)
    - Doane Appraisal Report (Box 18, Folder 255)
    - NAR Farms and Monte Sacro Financial Status (Box 18, Folder 256)
    - Malnar, Ltd. Financial Status (Box 18, Folder 257)
    - Inlaca Stock Sale Memo (Box 18, Folder 258)
    - Index to Political Folders (Box 19, Folder 259)
      Relates to Folders 260-261
    - NAR Poltical Contributions, 1968-1974 (Box 19, Folder 260)
    - Political Committees and Officers (Box 19, Folder 261)
    - Index to Private Affairs (Box 19, Folder 262)
      Relates to Folders 263-271
    - NAR Associations (Box 19, Folder 264)
    - Biographical Information (Box 19, Folder 267)
    - NAR Past Associations (Box 19, Folder 270)
    - NAR Statement, September 23, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 271)
    - Additional Documents, Not Categorized (Box 19, Folder 272)
    - NOT USED (Box 19, Folder 273)
    - Additional Documents, Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF) Annual Report, 1971-1973 (Box 19, Folder 274)
    - Index to Public Life (Box 19, Folder 275)
      Relates to Folders 276-283
    - Index to Documents Submitted to the Library of Congress (Box 19, Folder 276)
    - NAR Foreign Awards (Box 19, Folder 277)
    - List of Gifts from Foreign Heads of State (Box 19, Folder 278)
    - The Berlinger Report (Box 19, Folder 279)
    - Countries Visited by NAR for U.S. Government (Box 19, Folder 280)
    - 1969 Presidential Mission to Latin America Description (Box 19, Folder 281)
    - Critical Choices Commission, Third Century Corporation Members (Box 19, Folder 282)
    - Critical Choices Commission, Topics and Contributors (Box 19, Folder 283)
    - NAR Press Releases on Confirmation (Box 19, Folder 284)
  - "The Rockefeller Financial Group," by James C. Knowles (Box 20, Folder 285)
  - Senate Rules Committee - Member Biographies (Box 20, Folder 286)
    Materials concerned with the proceedings of the United States Senate Rules Committee on the nomination of NAR.
  - Senate Rules Committee - Bound Volume of the Hearings, September 23-26, November 13-15, 18, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 287)
  - Senate Rules Committee - Senate Committee Report, December 3, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 288)
  - Senate Rules Committee - Index to Hearings By Issue (Box 20, Folder 289)
  - Senate Rules Committee - Index to Hearings By Issue (Box 20, Folder 290)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - Robert R. Douglas (RRD) Copy (Box 20, Folder 291)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - Robert R. Douglas (RRD) Copy (Box 20, Folder 292)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - Joseph W. Ernst (JWE) Copy (Box 21, Folder 293)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - Joseph W. Ernst (JWE) Copy (Box 21, Folder 294)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - John E. Lockwood (JEL) Copy (Box 21, Folder 295)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Monday, September 23, 1974 - John E. Lockwood (JEL) Copy (Box 21, Folder 296)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Tuesday, September 24, 1974 - Robert R. Douglas (RRD) Copy (Box 21, Folder 297)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Tuesday, September 24, 1974 - Joseph W. Ernst (JWE) Copy (Box 21, Folder 298)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Tuesday, September 24, 1974 - Joseph W. Ernst (JWE) Copy (Box 21, Folder 299)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Tuesday, September 24, 1974 - John E. Lockwood (JEL) Copy (Box 21, Folder 300)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Wednesday, September 25, 1974 - Joseph W. Ernst (JWE) Copy (Box 21, Folder 301)
  - Senate Rules Committee -Transcripts of Proceedings, Wednesday, September 25, 1974 - John E. Lockwood (JEL) Copy (Box 21, Folder 302)